# **Professional Summary**

Top Skills: Creating alignment, translating strategy to execution, developing others

**Career Summary:** I like to tackle big problems and create structure out of chaos. I specialize in large global, cross functional programs. I have led teams for 11+ years, ~7 years directly as a people manager. I am usually described as strategic, pragmatic, technical, and insightful to organizational drivers.

## **Experience**

#### Transformation Lead, Red Hat Consulting

November 2021 - Current

- <u>Summary</u>: Lead client transformation from strategy development to team formation to iterative execution;
  Open Innovation Labs recognized by Computing and Fast Company awards for digital transformation
- Established new programs to deliver faster, easier-to-use IT services for clients in tech, shipping, and government services industries
- Led internal Red Hat mission and vision setting for Customer Success and Strategic Programs divisions
- Taught "DevOps Culture and Practices" course for internal Red Hat staff and external clients

### IT Operations PMO Manager, ExxonMobil

October 2020 - October 2021

- Summary: lead program manager for portfolio of all IT Operations products and trains (~3k staff)
- Led IT Operations transformation (~3k staff) from functional silos to a value stream based product model
- Led 13 staff located in the US, Argentina, Hungary, and Malaysia responsible for portfolio operations, product and program team coaching, and business transformation
- Coached program teams, project managers, and executives to set investment strategy with product roadmaps, program and portfolio metrics, and objective setting
- Recognized by IT executives for influencing change and driving organizational agility

## Lean Portfolio Manager & Agile Coach, ExxonMobil

December 2019 - October 2020

- <u>Summary:</u> lead program manager for portfolio of all infrastructure products and trains (120+ projects and initiatives, ~1k staff)
- Aligned product managers, program managers, project managers, etc. across multiple divisions
- Led Kaizen events with customer feedback to identify improvement opportunities and experiments
- Developed and stewarded portfolio metrics (throughput, investment, etc.) in Azure DevOps and PowerBI
- Coached program, project, and product managers on Agile principles including building trust, impediment removal, flow, minimum viable product, organizational design, investment strategy, and objective setting

#### Infrastructure Engineering Capability Manager, ExxonMobil

July 2018 - November 2019

- Summary: established, managed, and mentored 5 new product teams (~40 staff) in the US and Canada
- Developed capability management model, staffing pipeline, and career path for new roles
- Modernized staff tech skills by developing a persona based skill framework and skills runway

#### Outbound Internet Product Manager, ExxonMobil

March 2018 - June 2018

- Summary: led 2 network security teams of 14 staff located in the US, Argentina, and Hungary
- Managed outbound internet service for 100k+ users and inbound traffic for 2k+ applications
- Provided application high availability, security, And remote access via Application Delivery Controllers

## Global Innovation Labs Product Owner, ExxonMobil

November 2014 - February 2018

- Summary: Piloted first product team at ExxonMobil as a service to accelerate technology adoption
- Led cross functional team of 13 staff in the US, Brazil, Argentina, and Malaysia
- Enabled 200+ projects and proof-of-concepts through consultation, resourcing, and issue resolution
- Earned positive Net Promoter Scores by engaging and addressing needs of 20+ customer personas

#### **International Travel Sabbatical**

March 2014 - October 2014

Backpacked Asia and South America; completed spanish immersion program (EAFIT University, Medellin)

#### Additional Roles, ExxonMobil

July 2008 - March 2014

- UNIX Team Lead: led team of 9 staff in the US and Canada to manage lifecycle of 2k+ Linux servers
- eBusiness Team Lead: developed best practices for SharePoint and Web Hosting services
- Software Licensing Analyst: coordinated software deployment for IT and business users

#### Education

## The University of Texas at Austin - McCombs School of Business

May 2008

Bachelors of Business Administration, Management Information Systems major, Finance minor

## Other

#### **Business Skills**

Change Management, Design Thinking, Lean, Process Improvement, Value Stream Analysis, Portfolio Management, Investment Strategy, Governance, Objective Setting, OKRs, Organizational Design, Product Management, Program Management, Project Management, Budgeting, Big Room Planning

#### **Technical Skills**

IT Infrastructure, Databases, Python, Git, PowerQuery, PowerBI, Azure DevOps, Jira, AWS, SDLC, Linux, OpenShift

## Certifications

- SAFe Program Consultant 5 (SPC)
- AWS Certified Cloud Practitioner (RRSYE6GK5JQQ1GGB)

#### Languages

Native English speaker, experienced in Spanish